"It is better to receive an injury than to inflict one."
Cicero, "Tusculan Disputations"
Regarding the results of your final exam...
You all passed.
Hell yeah!
We're moving on for sure!
Awesome! You kidding me?!
Everyone?
We get to stay together!
That's fantastic!
I'm so happy!
For once, I'm unable to find
fault with the result anywhere.
That test was easy-peasy!
Says the class joke!
Says the guy with the lowest score.
Hey, don't say that!
You really are stupid.
Only stupid people call people stupid!
You're both stupid.
Shut up!
However...
Even with the year's final exam,
we haven't seen a single expulsion.
This is unprecedented in
the history of this school.
Therefore, we will have to
hold a follow-up special exam.
Huh?!
How come?
What in the world?
This is totally out of nowhere!
It's crazy!
Why do we have to do this?!
Unbelievable!
Tell us why!
The school admits that you've done very well.
Then what's the deal, huh?
Yeah!
End-of-Year Test           Total Ranking
We, the teachers,
don't take the task of burdening you
with an unexpected exam lightly.
So Chabashira doesn't like how
the school's reacting, either?
You have no right to refuse.
Teacher, what kind of exam is it?
The special exam...
will be a class vote.
3rd Season
Classroom
of
the
Elite
Classroom of
the Elite
I will now explain the
rules of the class vote.
In four days, you will
evaluate your classmates,
voting for three students
who are worthy of praise,
and three students who are worthy of censure.
The student with the most positive
votes will receive a special reward—
a new privilege known
as a "protection point."
A protection point?
It allows its user to negate an
expulsion they've qualified for.
You kidding me?!
Wow!
That's awesome!
That's amazing!
Really?
That's the best privilege ever!
That's a rather extreme reward.
Does something negative happen
to the three lowest placers?
Only one of them will be affected.
The purpose of the exam is
to total up votes received,
with positive votes adding points
and negative votes subtracting them,
to determine a single top
and single bottom placer.
The single... bottom placer?
As for why the school is using the
extraordinary measure of protection points...
It's because this is one test
that most likely cannot end
without someone getting expelled.
That's right. The lowest placing student...
will be expelled from this school.
Huh? Expelled?!
No freaking way!
After we passed, even...
It can't be...
In addition,
the protection point received
by the highest placing student
cannot be transferred to others.
Which means someone will
be expelled for sure.
Though simple, this may
be the cruelest test yet.
I don't get this!
Are we seriously talking
about expelling someone?
Yes.
But for once, the class will not be
penalized when the expulsion takes place.
The expulsion itself is the penalty!
A protection point is
an extraordinary reward.
But it comes with an appropriately
extraordinary risk.
I fully understand that
you find it unreasonable.
But now that it's done,
you must follow the rules,
and undertake the special exam.
That's how the world works.
Sakayanagi's father, the chairman,
didn't seem like the type to
conduct unreasonable exams, but...
Let's not lose hope just yet!
We've always found a way through before.
There's got to be a way to
prevent expulsion this time!
Hirata-kun is right.
We need to come together as a class and
make sure all the votes come out equally.
No, that won't help you.
You'll be forced to repeat the
vote until someone is expelled.
In addition, you'll be casting one positive
vote for a student in another class.
So it will be impossible for a single
class to fully manipulate the result.
But earlier, you said "most likely" expelled...
The use of private points
could change the equation.
If you can pay twenty million points,
you can potentially cancel an expulsion.
Twenty million points?
That's way too many points
to pool for one person!
Which means, after the test,
someone from this class is...
What the heck are we gonna do?!
This is the worst test possible!
Shut up, Yamauchi!
What's your problem?
Hey... you're not gonna cast a
negative vote for me, are you?!
She's not gonna tell you who she's voting for.
Yeah, I knew it!
I guess I'll have to vote for you guys, then!
How unsightly.
This is a test about looking
forward at our next two years.
Well, you're not exactly
in a safe spot, are you?
You understand so little, Red Hair-kun.
What?!
The fact that there's no penalty to the class
makes it an excellent opportunity
to delete an undesirable classmate.
Such as one of your incompetent
friends, perhaps.
Incompetent?
Shut the hell up!
Calm down. Let's all stay cool.
You don't have to worry, Hirata!
It's not like you're gonna
end up on the bottom!
Hey—
You're the safest one here.
It's not guaranteed for me, either!
It's not guaranteed for you, huh?
Yeah, right. You're the one safe man here.
Sure is nice being popular, huh?
Yeah, he doesn't have to
worry about being expelled!
Hirata-kun...
Yeah, so just back off.
I'm talking to Koenji right now.
That's enough, Sudo-kun.
Suzune?
There's still some time before the vote.
Let's use that time to think up what to do.
As I'm sure you're aware, blank votes
and abstentions will not be allowed.
Votes for yourself or multiple votes for
the same person are also not allowed.
I understand that this test
will be difficult for you,
but these are the rules
as decided by the school.
As long as you're attending this
school, you must follow these rules.
Now, we will hold the vote in four days.
Do you understand?
You can't do this to us!
Boy, this really stinks, huh?
Isn't there any way to get around it?
Planning out our votes is the only way.
I do have a suggestion.
What would you think about us
coordinating our votes as a group?
You mean, write each other
for the positive votes?
Yeah.
It won't guarantee us a place at the top,
but cooperating to avoid placing
last is probably for the best.
But is that all right?
The teacher said trying to arrange
the vote wouldn't help.
Even if we don't do it,
other groups surely will.
I'm in favor of covering
for each other as a group.
I wouldn't want to lose anyone here.
N-Neither do I!
It's settled, then.
Then let's get ahead of the game
and talk to some others.
No, we should stay under the
radar until the test is over.
So that we don't end up
deliberately targeted?
Yes. In this test,
if someone gets negative votes
focused on them, there's no defense.
In this test,
the lowest in the class hierarchy will
likely become negative vote sinks.
I see. We've got to lie low until the test, then.
Yeah.
I suppose I'll have to take action, then.
3rd Season
Classroom
of
the
Elite
Classroom of
the Elite
Discourse on Decadence
Ango Sakaguchi
He's been rather quiet lately, hasn't he?
Horikita.
You seem to have time to kill, Ryuen-kun.
I was wondering who it might be.
So it's you, Suzune.
And...
Your perpetual tagalong.
So? How can I help you?
What do you intend to do on
the upcoming special exam?
Nothing.
So you don't intend to fight to
make sure you're not expelled?
Hard to say.
I'm sure many people would
be happy to see you expelled.
For better or worse,
you've done too much here.
No one's going to reach out to help you.
Seeing as you're my enemy,
taking me out now would be
your best course of action.
Once I'm gone, Class D won't
stand a chance against you.
You think quite highly of yourself.
But you lack the talent
that a true leader needs.
That's why you fell to Class D.
True enough.
As this might be our last conversation,
could you tell me one thing?
If someone like you,
stuck in a hopeless situation,
wanted to engage seriously with this test,
do you think you could escape being expelled?
What a stupid question.
Of course I could.
Empty confidence, but typical.
Satisfied now?
Or do you want me to tell
you my plan for survival?
No.
Hearing it might lead me
right into your hands.
Still, thank you.
Seeing you accept reality
helps me to do what needs to be done.
What needs to be done?
If we can't avoid expelling someone,
I need to determine who's actually worthy,
and see that their sentence is carried out.
That could end up bouncing right back at you.
If it does, I suppose I'll have to accept
that this was the limit of my abilities.
Sounds like empty confidence to me.
It's not that easy to kill someone.
I can do it.
From the moment I came here, I've never
shown mercy to students who held me back.
You can't do it.
How would you know that?
I know all about you.
I can see the hints of
reluctance behind your words.
If you can't even face your own brother,
you're not prepared to do anything.
You don't actually know what to do, do you?
And you've already gotten comfortable
in your little class dynamic.
You can't possibly be level-headed about it.
The only ones who can, maybe, are me,
and Sakayanagi, who sees her classmates
as nothing more than pawns.
Despite all your confidence,
you don't really have a way out, do you?
What makes you think that?
Because at the end of the day,
you will be expelled.
Which is why I'm sitting
back and accepting it.
Don't let this chance get away, now.
I don't actually think I want Ryuen expelled.
He's completely bluffing.
No matter how he struggles,
he's going to be expelled for sure.
I wonder.
He really may have a plan.
Even if he reformed and apologized now,
he'd still get the same negative votes.
You're right.
A direct engagement wouldn't work.
Then that's the end of it.
But he did have a point back there.
What do you mean?
You probably should face your brother
at least once before he graduates.
I don't expect my brother to
be willing to meet with me.
Much as I dislike it, you're the
only one he has any interest in.
I suppose, if you say so.
I don't like how you said that.
She still has a powerful
complex about her brother.
What is it?
Hey, you got any advice for
what I should do on this test?
Have any groups begun to form around you?
Yeah, a few.
I'm sure everyone's afraid of expulsion.
So am I! I don't know
how many people hate me.
I wouldn't be surprised if you
received a few negative votes, yeah.
Hey, you're supposed to deny
that one, even if it's not true.
The best thing to do for now is lie low.
Fine. I won't stir the pot.
But your breakup with Hirata may
end up being a point in your favor.
If you were still dating Hirata,
who's quite popular with the girls,
one might have expected there to
be students who wanted to expel you
in order to drive you two apart.
Wow, scary.
But you might be right.
You're lucky.
No one notices you,
your grades are average...
Who are you gonna put in negative votes for?
I intend to choose those who will be
a negative to the class going forward.
Wow, that's cold.
Though I guess that's what you do...
If we can't avoid expelling someone,
it's the only logical choice.
Hey, you're not gonna say that's me, are you?
You're very important to the class.
I'd never eliminate you.
Y-Yeah, right?
I mean, of course!
If groups are forming, votes will likely
relate to something other than grades.
Seriously?
If you see some guiding principle
forming behind negative class votes,
let me know right away.
Okay. I'll call you right away.
Later, then!
Sure.
He's running late.
I guess it's really not
nice to ambush someone...
But...
I've been waiting.
Morning, Ayanokoji-kun!
I'm going on ahead.
Sure. See you later.
Morning, Ayanokoji-kun!
Oh. Good morning, Ichinose.
Um, so...
It's another cold day, huh?
I suppose.
Have you agreed to walk to school
with anyone in particular?
No.
Then... could I walk with you?
Sure.
The upcoming test is going to
be hard on Class B, I suppose?
Oh... yeah. I guess it will.
It might be our hardest test yet, even.
I bet.
But we just have to figure
something out, right?
You're not going to drop out, are you?
Oh, come on...
I didn't say that.
Your classmates aren't going to
write your name down, you know.
I didn't say I was going to drop out.
It's written on your face.
I-Is it?
I didn't mean literally.
Oh, right.
I guess not...
You want to sacrifice yourself
to protect someone else?
Not... quite.
I just feel like I have to take
on more risk in this fight.
But let's not get too deep into strategy.
We're in different classes, after all.
That's true.
Will you be okay, Ayanokoji-kun?
I'm not sure.
Would you like me to write you down for
my positive vote for another class?
You don't have to do that.
I'm not worthy of that vote.
That's not true!
You're very deserving of it.
Then I may ask you for that, just in case.
Sure, I'll keep it in mind.
Sure.
I really am glad I got
to speak with him today.
Ayanokoji-kun.
Do you have a moment?
Well... I should go.
Sure.
Later!
Did you find the extra exam unreasonable?
I suppose.
There's a reason why they're doing it.
My father, the chairman,
was recently suspended.
Someone may have a larger plan in mind.
This test was arranged at the last
minute in order to expel someone...
Does that seem possible to you?
You mean, me?
It would explain why the school was
plotting something this unreasonable.
Would it mean that man is involved, then?
That being the case, I'd like
to postpone our competition.
You're free to do as you like.
Thank you very much.
Now I can focus on matters within Class A.
However...
Since we're calling a ceasefire,
I won't be doing anything to sabotage
you on the test, Ayanokoji-kun.
Are you sure you want to promise that?
If I do end up doing something
to damage you in the results,
I will accept it as my own loss.
You'll be free to refuse our
next competition, as well.
Though if I end up as a target
for negative votes in this exam,
there won't be a next competition.
That's very true.
There won't be any sudden betrayals
before our fight happens?
Surely you jest.
The moment the test was announced,
I knew who I was going to expel.
Katsuragi Kohei-kun.
That's about what I expected.
What does Class C intend to do?
I'm not getting involved.
Really?
From Class D, I'm sure it will be Ryuen-kun.
The only mystery is Class B.
Seeing who from that close-knit
class will be expelled
will be the greatest
enjoyment from this test.
Now, we'll compete at the last
special exam of the year.
It's a promise.
Right.
I've been waiting.
President Nagumo...
Regarding the private point
matter we discussed...
E-Er...
Date me, Honami.
That's the condition.
Simple, isn't it?
I have to protect everyone.